曾经有一种计算机在日本流行
PC-9800 系列
它的昵称是 98，在日本人之间非常流行
曾经几乎 90 % 的日本计算机是 PC-98
到了 90 年代末期，PC-98 的时代结束了
NEC 也就改为生产 PCAT 兼容机
你所看到的笔记本就是 PC-98 系列中的一款
（PC-9821Nx，当时售价 560000 円）
这台电脑距离发售已经有二十多年了，成色依然很棒
它被一个人翻新了
他就是肝杉孝雄
在 PC-98 全盛时期，个人计算机是很昂贵的产品
PC-98 昂贵的价格使得很多厂商眼红
在那时，肝杉孝雄买不起 PC-98
然而，肝杉孝雄的一位土豪朋友就有一台 PC-98
机身全白色，有棱有角
肝杉孝雄十分羡慕，也想要一台 PC-98
“我是个学生，没有钱，所以我想让我的父母帮我买。”
父亲：“PC-98 多少钱？”
肝杉孝雄: "我想便宜的话大概二三十万円。"
父亲：“别瞎说什么蠢话了。”
于是父亲没有给他买 PC-98
看来他的父亲对此感到很遗憾，于是他从办公室带回来一台电脑
父亲：“这就是你要的 PC-98。”
肝杉孝雄很高兴，但是等他一开箱他惊呆了
这个 PC-98 的成色很糟糕，有很多烟灰尘土，划痕也很多
黯淡发黄的液晶屏
烟灰撒在机器上的痕迹
用倒是能用，但和我期待的完全不一样
肝杉孝雄很沮丧，但是他并不甘心
为了能将电脑清理干净，我用抹布擦拭
然而，就算抹布变脏了，电脑也干净不起来
就算把二手电脑用抹布擦干净了，那顶多也是表面没有灰尘的二手物品
即便过了十年二十年，肝杉孝雄的自卑情绪依然没有消失
此后，他成为了一个社团的成员
他用自己的钱买了一台新电脑，然而并不满意
肝杉孝雄经历了多年的经验积累，已经拥有了足够的动手能力
我已经学会了我应该要做的，我觉得我现在应该可以把 PC-98 翻修得跟新的一样
他决定通过自己的能力动手翻新 PC-98 来消除自己的自卑情绪
自卑情绪就是翻新的动力
黯淡的液晶屏
发黄肮脏的键盘
电解电容也漏液了
有人打趣说：这根本就不是二手电脑
这是废品ww
会毁掉软盘的软驱
光驱音乐跑偏，托盘推不回去
处理的时候排线裂开了
处理的时候外壳酥了
复活吧！98！！
肝杉孝雄去买了用于修复的配件
它不但成色很糟糕，而且还缺少了一些本应连接的配件
这个二手 PC-98 没有光驱
他在日拍买到的光驱成色并不好
他不能正常听音乐，也不能推仓
在市面上能买到的 PC-98 配件和他年纪差不多大
“我感觉我简直就是从负数开始……”
他调整了光驱的激光头
他还让开仓退仓过程变得顺滑了
这就修好了，坑就开始了，他并没有弃坑
他开始拆开他的 PC-98，但是他对做什么一脸茫然
主板覆盖满了烟灰，他仔细做了清理
这两块主板上有相当多的电解电容
电脑上的电容寿命很短，很快就会漏液，搞不好还会腐蚀主板
他也觉得这是巨大隐患
一些漏液的电容被小心地拆开了
幸好主板没有被腐蚀
然后他替换掉了所有的电解电容
就是得这样……
我就一直期待着把它修好，这样就很棒了
我已经拆开过一次了，我会面临很多问题的
哈？就这么详细？
要花多少时间来修复？要花多少钱？我能自己修好吗？
我才注意到，要面临的挑战很大，我心里没底。
我真的在做什么可怕的事情吗？
嗯……就酱
他说：当人们想做什么事情的时候这就是他们的动力，
这也就是想得到大家的认可的想法
这是连接本体和显示屏之间的线缆
排线上的绝缘胶带已经老化，胶水也开始劣化
他就进行清理并重新绑上了新的绝缘胶带
用于存放设置和时钟的纽扣型 CMOS 电池也已经被替换
Since it came so far, it was provisionally assembled.
Well, can this start? "Switch finger pressing" trembled.
As if nothing had happened...
PC-98 is done.
"I was very nervous because I had been broken many times before I tried to fix it. hahaha..."
Takao smiled happily. There was no front teeth there.
Next, He started a tired body case.
He polished the entire PC. It is a work of peeling dirty skin.
Suddenly there was an accident. A part of the case was missing.
Plastic that has been 20 years old will deteriorate and weaken.
Of course, even when disassembling, the fastener may be chipped.
"This is a matter of course, at that time, just repair that part."
Takao was very calm.
The surface is painted finish by airbrush.
The paint was toned by color of the part not damaged.
It is mat. But a slight gloss.
He wanted to reproduce elegant skin just like a brand new.
The greatest difficulty
"98NOTE" logo
It was formed by many fine thread-like prints.
He anticipated a difficult flight.
However, if he leave it alone, PC-98 will never be like a brand new one.
"This is a critical moment."
Takao was inspired.
He got tired of the fine work.
Takao could not do it well, He repeated the failure many times.
Every time it failed, He had to peel off all the paint and paint it from the beginning.
The number of empty paint bottles increased.
He bought the same paint, looking for a neighborhood shop.
"Fail, but sometimes I knew when I failed.
I thought this was a matter of accuracy. It will be better by overcoming it."
"So I... I had to become a PC myself!
In other words, by myself becoming a precision machine!!"
"it is ---
The "98NOTE" logo was reproduced in this way.
It is not over yet.
Next is the rubber feet that was once gray. It was dirty and black.
Takao sticks to the same color and shape.
Although he was looking for Akihabara and a DIY store, he could not find it.
In the meantime, he found a company that produces custom rubber feet.
He ordered the company as if asking for help.
The sensation of a new item increased at once.
He felt the effect of such accessories strongly.
The cushion rubber between the display and the main body was similarly dirty.
Besides, it was a state where things like oil seeped out.
As the cushion rubber had a simple shape, he cut the gray rubber and made it for himself.
The keyboard was dirty by the tabacco stain.
He washed it and soaked it in the kitchen bleach.
It disappears in the tobacco stain and the color recovers.
However, there was still a used keybord.
Key top that was struck repeatedly with your finger. The surface should have been matte finish.
Unfortunately, however, a dull luster appeared.
The word "beautiful used keybord" was perfect.
He picked out key tops with shine and got a little matte paint.
Key tops were reborn like new.
Alright. He assembled it and turned on the power. PC-98... revive!
Cruel reality. The exterior, which was reborn like a brand new, made the darkness of the display more prominent.
"Even if you fix it, this is a used item"
He felt that the display insisted that way.
He did not give up.
It was fortunate that there were no scratches, cracks, dot missing on the display.
He said that he had to give up play if he had such symptoms.
There really is a PC that can not regain its original form.
I feel sorry but that is reality. "
As he muttered so, he seemed a little sad.
Degradation of display brightness and color.
It is due to exhaustion of the backlight.
Currently LED backlights are mainstream, but cold cathode tubes were often used at that time.
A narrow rod-like glass tube emits light.
It is almost like a fluorescent light source.
It is delicate. Moreover, it takes a voltage of several hundred volts.
Handling required attention.
"I was very scared, what would I do if I break it?
What would I do if I get an electric shock? I thought so."
As I said, Takao laughed proudly this time.
As he became friends, he began to show various expressions.
I exchanged it and caused it to emit light.
The brightness was completely different.
It was bright from just after startup.
Yellowish is gone.
Finally He decided to repair the mouse and power adapter.
This is the last spurt.
Glossy parts. Without glossy parts.
He sticked to how to finish the surface.
He polished persistently fast.
Usually, this type of gloss can not be produced in the molding process of the factory.
Polish too. He thought so.
In the case of the mattress, it painted by masking the logo part of the manufacturer.
He wiped a black, troubling, serpentine cable over the day.
He used detergent and absolute ethanol, but when it still can not get dirty, He used thinner.
The hardened cable regained its suppleness by being clean.
When everything was over, he noticed that his palm was cracked.
PC-98 finally reproduced. He thought so.
However, trouble occurred when accessing the floppy disk to install the OS.
When writing to a floppy disk, a phenomenon occurred that the floppy disk could not be read.
It was when he was disassembling to maintain a floppy disk, relying on the web.
He was careless. He broke the flexible cable.
Bad events were overlapping.
"The accessory of PC-98 is an exhausted resource,
I felt strongly the guilt feeling of breaking such accessories
I thought that I did sorry."
Fortunately, we were able to obtain a floppy disk drive at a shop dealing with PC-98 accessories.
Even now, there is a shop that maintains and sells PC-98 accessories and main body like this.
PC - 98 's accessories are expensive because it is valuable now, not cheap.
But he thought. "I have a group.
In this way, his PC-98 was revived.
His inferiority complex disappeared with PC tobacco stain and dirt.
At that time, he had no feeling of joy by what he achieved.
He thought he resembled a feeling of security when his work was done everyday.
The light of the morning sun from the window of a few times was bright.
Finally, we tried a few questions to Takao.
Then he invited me to a late night drive.
He says his heart will be healed by driving, he will feel honest.
He says the heart will never be disturbed.
"Driving will relieve your mind.
I will have the heart of Buddha and answer your questions. "
We started asking him a question.
Q:For Takao, what kind of thing is "new product"?
That is the easiest question.
I will win if it is said to the other player that "That is a new PC."
However, if I told my opponent, "It's a PC that looks good," I am defeated.
Because it is a praise for used PC.
Q:It was a difficult task. But can not we make it easier as we can do?
I think that it would be nice if there was a service that could exchange exterior parts, but at present it is not.
So, there is no other way than we can move our hands.
The state of a new article is transient.
And it is very difficult to regain it.
Q:Is your PC-98 OS Windows?
I will not install Windows on this PC.
Installing Windows on the PC-98 in the past has become popular.
However, it was very poor in cost performance.
I think everyone is scrupulous.
Q:So what is the OS?
It is NEC version of DOS.
Q:What can you do with that DOS?
I can not do anything in particular. What I can do with this PC-98 can be done with the current general PC.
In the first place do not you understand that you did not restore to make something with this PC-98?
Q:Huh? So, why did you restore this PC-98?
This is my habit! habit, religion, drag. It is such kind of thing.
It is not a problem you open your mouth!
Q:Regardless of personal computer, is not your front teeth brand new?
He seems to be excited, so I will finish the interview.
Finally I will part with you while watching the opening of PC-98 game.
Thank you for watching it for a long time!